Guide to the Records of the Associated Colleges of Upper New York (ACUNY) MC.82
New York University Archives
Records of the Associated Colleges of Upper New York
1946-1954
New York University Archives
Associated Colleges of Upper New York.
MC.82
2.5 Linear Feet
The Associated Colleges of Upper New York (ACUNY) was New York State's answer to the nationwide dilemma of assimilating World War II veterans into the educational system. This collection contains the papers of Harold O. Voorhis, Vice-Chancellor and Secretary of NYU, in his role in acting-Trustee for ACUNY in the stead of Chancellor Harry Chase.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
ACUNY
Metropolitan Survey
Scope and Content Note
The ACUNY records of the Voorhis collection span from 1946 to 1952 with a single document dated January 7, 1954. The collection is fairly complete, especially between 1947 and 1948. Materials include copies of convocation exercises, clippings, student bulletins, and correspondence between Trustees, ACUNY personnel, and college presidents and officials. Their letters illustrate the decision to extend the charter, the evolution of the State University system, and the ability and concern of these officials in time of an educational crisis. Minutes and financial and research reports have very few gaps. They date from the first formal minutes of the Board of Trustees (June 17, 1946) to the accountants' final Report on Examination (August 6, 1946 - May 25, 1951).
ACUNY was respected for its academic excellence but there were tensions within the system. The problems generally involved Sampson College. In April 1947, Dr. Chauncey Louttit, Dean of Faculty, Sampson, was forced to resign. There are newspaper clippings of the dissatisfaction with housing, the food service, and the fear of communist influence. A small group of students claimed that the administration wire-tapped their phones, illegally searched their rooms and censored their newspaper. The faculty resented their posts being terminated because of the decrease in enrollment, which was a result of the college's closing in June 1949.
History of ACUNY
The Associated Colleges of Upper New York (ACUNY), 1946-1951, was New York State's answer to the nationwide dilemma of assimilating World War II veterans into the educational system. The organization owed its beginnings chiefly to New York State Governor Thomas Dewey. In March 1946 the Governor held a conference of 85 New York State college presidents to evaluate the issue. Earlier studies by the State Education Department found that the existing colleges could not sufficiently absorb the anticipated 100,000 veterans seeking college-level education under the G.I. Bill of Rights.
ACUNY was a joint venture between the state and private colleges of New York. Under the auspices of the Governor, the State Education Department, and ten college presidents, ACUNY received its charter from the Board of Regents on May 17, 1946. The charter awarded ACUNY nonprofit status and set its objective to provide the first two years of college for any qualified veteran who was rejected from one of the state's four-year colleges because of "insufficient housing, overcrowded classrooms and lack of instructional staff."
Expediency was necessary in order to insure that the emergency facilities were established and ready to function by the fall semester 1946. The temporary Army and Navy facilities of upstate New York held enough housing and classroom space to alleviate overcrowding. The military sites chosen were the United States Naval Training Center (Sampson College, opened September 15, 1946), Rhoads Hospital (Mohawk College, opened October 16, 1946) and Fort Plattsburg (Champlain College, opened September 23, 1946). In February 1947 another center was launched in Middletown at the request of the community.
In July 1946, Dr. John S. Allen, Executive Director of Higher Education, and Dr. J. Hillis Miller, Associate Commissioner of Education, realized that New York City was heavily affected by the problem. ACUNY agreed to extend its trusteeship to include eight New York metropolitan college presidents as well as the Superintendent of Schools in New York City, John Wade. Vice-Chancellor and Secretary of NYU, Harold Voorhis served as acting-Trustee for Chancellor Harry Chase, who was preoccupied with NYU's Medical Center campaign. Edmund Day, Chairman of the Board of Trustees, ACUNY, appointed Voorhis Chairman of the Special Committee to investigate the New York City situation. In January 1947 the Committee reported that the establishment of an emergency college in the city was unnecessary.
Originally, ACUNY was to cease operation July 1, 1948; the emergency was only expected to last two years. But the charter was extended twice: once in 1948 for an additional year, and again in 1949 for an additional two years. ACUNY's President, Asa Knowles, left his post after the initial two-year period. Frederick A. Morse, the Executive Assistant for Higher Education in the State Education Department, was elected the new president by the Board of Trustees.
Under Morse, a new attitude developed at ACUNY; the institution actively sought prospective college students rather than supplementing the existing universities. It began sending out faculty members as recruiters to high schools and published an illustrated booklet.
The fates of the colleges differed. Mohawk College closed in June 1948, and Sampson College closed in June 1949. Champlain College went on to become the first liberal arts college of the State University of New York, and Middletown became a two-year community college. Overall, ACUNY's existence was successful despite the short-lived civil rights complaints of the faculty and students of Sampson in the spring of 1948. After the first two years of its existence, ACUNY managed to transfer its qualified students to four-year colleges to finish their college careers.
Sources:
Gilbert, Amy. ACUNY: The Associated Colleges of Upper New York. Ithaca, New York: Cornell University Press, 1950.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Provenance
The records were accessioned to the University Archives in March 1975.
Correspondence.; Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Universities and colleges |z New York (State); Rondileau, Adrian, 1912-; Louttit, C. M. (Chauncey McKinley), 1901-1956; Voorhis, Harold O.; Saville, Thorndike, 1892-1969; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951
- Series I: ACUNY
  - Administrative Manual #2, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Manual #2 (copy), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes (and Bylaws), Jun 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Sep 10, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Oct 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Jan 23, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Jun 18, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Dec 17, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Mar 25, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Nov 22, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes (copy), Nov 22, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Jun 15, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Jun 20, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, May 26, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes (copy), May 26, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees: Minutes, Jun 21, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Budget: Ending Jun 30, 1947 & Revised Estimated Financing Jul 1, 1947 - Jun 30, 1948, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Budget: Jul 1, 1947 - Jun 30, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Budget Forms and Estimated Requirements, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: General, 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Louttit, C.M. (Dean of Faculty, Sampson -- Problems at Sampson, Resignation), 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Saville, Thorndike (Dean of NYU School of Engineering), 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee: Minutes, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee: Resolutions, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial Report, Aug 6, 1946-May 25, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Financial Report, Aug 6, 1946-Mar 31, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial Report (Aug 6, 1946 - Jun 30, 1947), 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Financial Report (F/Y Jun 30, 1947) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial Report (F/Y Jun 30, 1948) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Financial Report (F/Y Jun 30, 1949) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report (F/Y Jun 30, 1950) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Inspection Reports of Campuses, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Maintenance and Operations, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Middletown Proposal Correspondence, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Middletown Proposal Report, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Petition for Extended Charter, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Printed Matter: Brochures (Photostats of Sampson newspaper, clippings), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Printed Matter: Clippings (Parade Magazine), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Printed Matter: Clippings (Problems at Sampson), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Printed Matter: Course Bulletins, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Printed Matter: Faculty Bulletins, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Printed Matter: Faculty Bulletins, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Printed Matter: Faculty Bulletins, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Printed Matter: Miscellaneous, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed Matter: Student Guides & Handbooks, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Report on Examination (F/Y Jun 30, 1947) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report on Examination (F/Y Jun 30, 1948) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report on Examination (F/Y Jun 30, 1949) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Report on Examination (F/Y Jun 30, 1950) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Report on Examination (F/Y May 25, 1951) (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series II: Metropolitan Survey
  - Correspondence: Day, Edmund (Chairman of the Board, ACUNY and President of Cornell University), 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Department of Higher Education (John Allen and J. Hillis Miller), 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: General, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Kastner (NYU Registrar), 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Rondileau, Adrian (Dean, Business Administration, ACUNY), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Rutgers University (Robert Clothier, President and William Speer, Director of Admissions), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - History of the Metropolitan Survey by Amy Gilbert, ACUNY Official Historian, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Metropolitan Survey: Newspaper Advertisement, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Press and Advertising Coverage, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Press Releases, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Printed Matter: Newspaper Clippings, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Reports: Dean Rondileau's Progess Reports I and II, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reports: Dean Rondileau's Progess Report III, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reports: Memorandum and Press Release Drafts, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Reports: Meeting of the Survey Committee, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reports: Metropolitan Survey Sampling Tables, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reports: Metropolitan Survey Sampling Tables, copy, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Reports: To the Board of Trustees, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Summary of Results and Log of Survey, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Survey Questionnaires, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 9)